{"tossups": [{"question": "This man was kidnapped by Thomas Hunt, who later sold him to local monks in the city of M\u00e1laga. Following that sale, this man travelled to North America, where he piloted a ship of settlers around Cape Cod to locate food, as ordered by William Bradford. Dying after contracting what was called \u201cIndian fever,\u201d for the point, who was this Native American known for acting as a liaison between the Patuxet [[pah-TUK-set]] tribe and the Pilgrims?", "answer": "<b><u>Squanto</u></b> (accept <b><u>Tisquantum</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A former slave in this position was killed by being thrown down steps by his son-in-law and run over in a chariot by his daughter. Using the ruse of festival games, a holder of this position committed the abduction of the Sabine [[SAY-been]] women to populate his city. The Cult of Mars and the Vestal Virgins were established by the second holder of this position, Numa Pompilius. Tarquin [[TAR-kwin]] the Proud was the last person to hold, for the point, what regal position legendarily established by Romulus?", "answer": "<b><u>King</u></b> of <b><u>Rome</u></b> (accept <b><u>Roman King</u></b>; or <b><u>Rex Romae</u></b>; accept words \"Ruler\" or \"Monarch\" in place of <b><u>King</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Operation Hectic was an SAS plot to assassinate this man and his aides by targeting their electoral headquarters with T-55 tank fire. This self-identified Marxist, who was replaced in a 2017 coup by Emmerson Mnangagwa [[mah-nahn-GAW-gwah]], signed the Lancaster House Agreement, toppling whites-only rule in Rhodesia. For the point, name this leader of the ZANU-Patriotic Front and long-time president of Zimbabwe.", "answer": "Robert <b><u>Mugabe</u></b> [[moo-GAH-beh]] (or Robert Gabriel <b><u>Mugabe</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This man's forces fought the Ragamuffin War, a rebellion started by nomadic cowhands known as<em> gauchos</em>. This ruler deployed the Marquis of Erval to rebuff Paraguayan president Francisco Solano Lopez's invasion during the War of the Triple Alliance. This man's daughter, Isabel, passed the Golden Law, emancipating all the enslaved people in their nation in 1888. The final Emperor of Brazil was, for the point, which member of the House of Braganza, known as \"The Magnanimous\"?", "answer": "Dom <b><u>Pedro II</u></b> (prompt on \u201cPedro\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A six-month-long occupation of this city began after several of Admiral Mayo's sailors were detained here, leading to the 1914 Tampico Affair. Winfield Scott and Matthew Perry organized the U.S. military's first large-scale amphibious assault in history to capture this port en route to Mexico City. For the point, name this Gulf of Mexico port city, at which Hern\u00e1n Cort\u00e9s first landed before conquering the Aztec Empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Veracruz</u></b> (accept Heroica <b><u>Veracruz</u></b> or Puerto de <b><u>Veracruz</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This political agreement was strengthened following Count Bernhard von B\u00fclow [[BYOO-\"low\"]] threatening war over supremacy in Morocco. Foreign Secretary Lord Lansdowne ended Britain's era of \"Splendid Isolation\" by entering into this agreement in 1904. Support for Serbia pulled this alliance into a continental war following the assassination of Franz Ferdinand in Sarajevo [[SAH-rah-YAY-voh]]. The Central Powers fought World War One against, for the point, what political alliance of the UK, France, and Russia?", "answer": "Triple <b><u>Entente</u></b> (accept <b><u>Entente</u></b> Cordiale [note: the \"Triple Entente\" was built on the earlier \"Entente Cordiale\"])", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man was forced to resign as chamberlain for the king of Prussia after publishing \"Diatribe of Doctor Akakia [[ah-kah-KYAH]],\" criticizing Pierre Louis Maupertuis [[moh-pehr-TWEE]]. This thinker stated the Holy Roman Empire was \"neither Holy, nor Roman, nor an Empire.\" This man satirized Gottfried Leibnitz [[LIBE-nitz]] through his character of Pangloss in a novella subtitled<em> Optimism</em>. The character Candide [[kahn-DEED]] was created by, for the point, which French Enlightenment author?", "answer": "<b><u>Voltaire</u></b> (accept Fran\u00e7ois-Marie <b><u>Arouet</u></b>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "A treaty negotiated by this man and Diego de Gardoqui [[gahr-DOH-kee]], which aimed to open Spanish New World ports to U.S. trade, was never ratified due to opposition by a Madison-Monroe coalition. A withdrawal of British forces from forts in the Northwest Territories and a \"most favored nation\" trading status was acquired by a 1795 treaty named for this diplomat. The first Supreme Court Chief Justice was, for the point, which Federalist from New York?", "answer": "John <b><u>Jay</u></b> (accept <b><u>Jay</u></b>'s Treaty)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This European man's namesake law code credits his ancestors, King Ina and King Offa, as being the first Brittonic men to be baptized. This man supposedly dressed as a bard to sneak into the city of Chippenham to gain intel prior to the Battle of Edington. This man, whose grandson Aethelstan united England, defeated the \"Great Heathen Army\" of the Viking leader Guthrum. For the point, name this \"Great\" king of Wessex and the Anglo-Saxons.", "answer": "<b><u>Alfred</u></b> the Great", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "After this artist designed an ashtray for Air India, they gifted him a baby elephant which was delivered to Cadaqu\u00e9s [[kah-dah-KESS]]. This monarchist was given the title \"1st Marquess of P\u00fabol [[POO-bohl]]\" following a visit from King Juan Carlos I. This artist was expelled by the leftist Andr\u00e9 Breton [[breh-TOHN]] and his fellow surrealists for his ardent support of the Franco regime. The<em> Persistence of Memory</em> was painted by, for the point, what eccentric Catalonian artist?", "answer": "Salvador <b><u>Dal\u00ed</u></b> (or Salvador Domingo Felipe Jacinto <b><u>Dal\u00ed</u></b> i Dom\u00e8nech)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "With his Wendat allies, this military leader defeated the Iroquois at the Battle of Sorel during the Beaver Wars. This captain of the<em> Don de Dieu</em> [[dohn-duh-DYUH]] improved on a map of the St. Lawrence River first charted by Jacques Cartier [[kar-TYEH]]. During the regency of Louis XIII [[\"the thirteenth]], Cardinal Richelieu [[reesh-LOO]] declared this man \"Governor of New France.\" The founder of Quebec City was, for the point, which French explorer, who names a lake shared between Vermont and New York?", "answer": "Samuel de <b><u>Champlain</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In this war, the traitorous city of Capua [[KAP-yoo-uh]] was made<em> ager publicus</em> [[AH-ger POO-blih-kuss]], losing its civic rights. Quintus Fabius Maximus implemented his namesake delaying \"Strategy\" following this war's disastrous Battle of Cannae [[KAN-nee]], the bloodiest in the Republic's history. Losing this war's Battle of the Great Plains led Hannibal to abandon his Italian campaign to return to North Africa. Scipio [[SKIP-ee-oh]] Africanus's victory at Zama effectively ended, for the point, what Roman-Carthaginian War?", "answer": "Second <b><u>Punic</u></b> War", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "The book<em> Team of Rivals</em> opens in the midst of this election year. The short-lived Constitutional Union party ran its first and only presidential candidate, Tennessee senator John Bell, during this election cycle. The Democrats split into two distinct Northern and Southern factions during this election, with one side running Stephen A. Douglas and the other John Breckinridge. For the point, name this electoral cycle which preceded the Civil War, ending in a victory for Abraham Lincoln.", "answer": "Election of <b><u>1860</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this war, the Count of Cavour sent a 15,000 man Sardinian expeditionary force, which proved critical during its Siege of Sevastopol [[seh-VASS-toh-pohl]]. The Earl of Cardigan led the ill-fated \"Charge of the Light Brigade\" during this war's Battle of Balaclava [[bah-lah-KLAH-vah]]. Florence Nightingale gained prominence during this conflict. For the point, what war, fought primarily on a namesake peninsula, halted Russian imperial expansion into the Black Sea?", "answer": "<b><u>Crimea</u></b>n War (accept Guerre de <b><u>Crim\u00e9e</u></b>; <b><u>Krymskaya</u></b> voyna; or <b><u>Vostochnaya</u> </b>voyna)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The first opera commissioned in this nation's language, titled<em> \u00d6zsoy</em> [[UHZ-soy]], is a retelling of a story from the<em> Shahnemah</em>. A ruler from what is today this nation named Selim III hosted operatic performances in the Topkapi Palace. In this modern nation, Pedrillo [[peh-DREE-yoh]] aims to rescue his lover Konstanze from the harem of Osmin in a Mozart work. Janissary music inspired<em> Abduction from the Seraglio</em> [[seh-RAH-lyoh]], a singspiel set in what is today, for the point, what Middle Eastern nation?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Turkey</u></b> (or <b><u>Turkiye</u></b> Cumhuriyeti; accept <b><u>Ottoman</u></b> Empire)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {}, {"question": "According to Francis Fukuyama's<em> The End of History and the Last Man</em>, this event represented the conclusion of the last challenge to liberal democracy as an ideology. Four months prior to this event, the Gang of Eight perpetrated the August Coup, though it was stopped by pro-Yeltsin forces. The reforms of Mikhail Gorbachev failed to prevent this political event. For the point, name this disintegration of a Communist nation into constituent countries like Ukraine, Kazakhstan, and Russia.", "answer": "<b><u>Dissolution</u></b> of the <b><u>USSR</u></b> (accept <b><u>Fall</u></b> of the <b><u>USSR</u></b> or other word forms which indicate the \"Soviet Union broke-up\"; accept <b><u>Soviet Union</u></b> or <b><u>CCCP</u></b> for \"USSR\"; do not accept or prompt on mentions of \"Russia\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Following various lawsuits, this organization committed Operation Freak-Out, which aimed to have reporter Paulette Cooper imprisoned. This organization infiltrated the IRS to purge information on their founder in Operation Snow White. This faith believes the Galactic Dictator Xenu [[ZEE-noo]] brought humans to Earth 75 million years ago. Since 1987, David Miscavige [[mis-KAV-idge]] has led, for the point, what \"Church\" founded by L. Ron Hubbard?", "answer": "Church of <b><u>Scientology</u></b> (accept <b><u>Scientologist</u></b>s)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "During this battle, a kamikaze squadron sank the carrier USS<em> Bismarck Sea</em>. Prior to this battle, Chester Nimitz claimed the Japanese would surrender the targeted island without a fight. Joe Rosenthal shot a partially-staged raising of the U.S. flag over Mount Suribachi [[soo-rih-BAH-chee]] during this battle. One of the last major battles of the Pacific Theatre was, for the point, what engagement on the namesake volcanic Japanese island?", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Iwo Jima</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A radiation leak nearly led to a total meltdown at Three Mile Island, a plant utilizing, for the point, what energy source created through fission?", "answer": "<b><u>Nuclear</u></b> Energy (accept <b><u>Nuke</u></b>Gate Scandal; accept \"Power\" in place of \"Energy\" and \"Atomic\" in place of \"Nuclear\")", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "In one speech, Abraham Lincoln stated \"give me one of [these taxes] and America will have the greatest nation on Earth.\" The effects of the Great Depression were worsened by one of these taxes passed by the Smoot-Hawley Act. The Nullification Crisis and the resignation of Vice President Calhoun occurred after one of [these taxes] \"of Abominations\" was passed in 1830. For the point, name these protective economic barriers passed to protect domestic industry.", "answer": "<b><u>Tariff</u></b>s (accept Protective <b><u>Tariff</u></b>; accept Smoot-Hawley <b><u>Tariff</u></b>; accept <b><u>Tariff</u></b> of Abominations)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "While tramping around this city, Ignatius Reilly bemoans society's loss of Platonic values like geometry in<em> A Confederacy of Dunces</em>. The Creole-descended Edna Pontellier [[pohn-tel-YEH]], an unhappy resident of this city, drowns herself in the Gulf of Mexico during<em> The Awakening</em>. Blanche Dubois [[doo-BWAH]] in<em> A Streetcar Named Desire</em> moves to the French Quarter in, for the point, what Southern U.S. city?", "answer": "<b><u>New Orleans</u></b> (accept La <b><u>Nouvelle-Orl\u00e9ans</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "This foodstuff is the most commonly used ingredient in a Caelius Apicius [[KAY-lee-us ah-\"PICK\"-ee-us]] manual,<em> De re culinaria</em> [[deh-reh-koo-lih-NAH-ree-ah]]. In medieval Nuremburg, this food's quality was regulated by its office of<em> Wurstlein</em> [[VURST-\"lean\"]]. In<em> Maccabees</em>, Jewish citizens openly refusing to eat this un-kosher food led to Antiochus [[an-TIE-oh-kuss]] IV's army attempting to kill them. For the point, name this meat forbidden in Islam, a food derived from swine.", "answer": "<b><u>Pork</u></b> (or <b><u>Ham</u></b>; accept synonymous answers involving food derived the meat of pigs)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "A remote lake in this range named the Roopkund is known for its high count of skeletons from far off lands like the Eastern Mediterranean Sea. Allied Pilots called the eastern end of this range \"The Hump\" due to its relative difficulty to cross while airlifting supplies to Republican China. Sherpa guide Tenzing Norgay and Edmund Hillary summited this range's highest peak in the 1950s. For the point, name this range which forms the boundary of Tibet and Nepal, the home range of Mount Everest.", "answer": "<b><u>Himalaya</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Himalaya</u></b>ns; or <b><u>Himalaya</u></b>n Mountains; accept Ganesh <b><u>Himal</u> </b>Range)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "The Conway Cabal collapsed after a visit to this site by delegates of the Continental Congress. Waterproof barrels prepared at this site were floated down the Delaware river in an attempt to destroy British sloops in the \"Battle of the Kegs.\" Teaching soldiers proper line formation and bayonet use, Friedrich von Steuben [[SHTOY-ben]] was elevated to drillmaster at this site. For the point, name this Pennsylvania winter encampment of 1777-1778 for Washington's Continental Army.", "answer": "<b><u>Valley Forge</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this nation, \"The Scream of La Villa de Los Santos\" began a major independence movement. The USS<em> Nashville</em> assisted this nation's soldiers stationed in Colon in repelling a Colombian invasion. During Operation Just Cause, the U.S. invaded this nation to depose<em> de</em> <em>facto</em> leader Manuel Noriega in 1989. For the point, name this Central American nation which contains a canal connecting the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Panama</u></b> (or Republica de <b><u>Panama</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "One pseudo-scientific method that claims to be able to cure this condition includes high doses of vitamin C and \"orthomolecular support,\" known as CEASE therapy. Leo Kanner first gave this term its modern usage and proposed the \"refrigerator mother\" theory, which has since been discarded. For the point, name this spectrum disorder characterized by difficulties in communication and social interaction.", "answer": "<b><u>Autism</u></b> spectrum disorder (accept <b><u>ASD</u></b>; accept <b><u>Autistic</u></b>; prompt on \"Asperger('s)\" before \"Kanner\")", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {}, {"question": "Following attacks on teachers for enforcing this policy in Travis County, Tom Leonard described the incidents as \"a few sad moments.\" In late August 2021, Oregon re-imposed this policy for outdoor activities. In Texas, executive order 35A prevented any city or county from enacting this policy. In Florida, public schools with this policy had their state funding frozen. For the point, name this COVID-19 pandemic policy that requires people to wear a covering over the face.", "answer": "<b><u>Mask Mandate</u></b>s (accept any answer indicating being required to wear a face<b><u>mask</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Herman S\u00f6rgel [[SUHR-gul]] devised the Panropa plan to increase usable land around this body by strategically building hydroelectric dams. Glass ingots and<em> Pistacia</em> [[pih-STAY-shuh]] resin were found in the Uluburun shipwreck in this sea off the coast of Bodrum. The development of the 50-rower<em> penteconter</em> vessel facilitated maritime trade across the eastern portion of this sea. For the point, name this European sea which was known as<em> Mare Nostrum</em> [[MAH-reh NOH-stroom]] to the Romans.", "answer": "<b><u>Mediterranean</u></b> Sea (prompt on smaller bodies within the Mediterranean like the \"Aegean Sea\")", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "A cabal of politicians and distillers working within this man's administration were revealed by Benjamin Bristow to be avoiding state taxes.<em> The New York Sun</em> reported how Republicans close to this president were getting kickbacks from a fake railroad company, which greatly inflated its own costs. The Credit Mobilier [[moh-beel-YEH]] Scandal and the Whiskey Ring affected, for the point, the administration of which former Union general and U.S. president?", "answer": "Ulysses S. <b><u>Grant</u></b> (accept Hiram Ulysses <b><u>Grant</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Two inmates named Vrba and Wentzler name a report outlining the layout of this site, convincing Mikl\u00f3s [[MEE-klohsh]] Horthy to halt his deportation edict. The head of the Theresienstadt [[teh-RAY-zyen-SHTAHT]] orchestra, Pavel Haas, was sent to this place in 1944. A sign at this complex claimed \"work sets you free,\" and this camp included the gas chambers at Birkenau. For the point, name this Nazi death camp in modern Poland, the deadliest of World War Two.", "answer": "<b><u>Auschwitz</u></b> Concentration Camp (or Konzentrationslager <b><u>Auschwitz</u></b>; accept <b><u>Auschwitz</u></b>-Birkenau)", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}